A Guide to the Senator Charles Waddell Scrapbooks, 1967-2001
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Senator Charles Waddell Scrapbooks, 1967-2001
Thomas Balch Library
OM 0022
4 oversized scrapbooks.
The Senator Charles Waddell Scrapbooks consist of four scrapbooks documenting the early decades of Charles Waddell's political career in Loudoun County.
Charles L. Waddell, Leesburg, VA
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Charles L. Waddell
Biographical Information
Born in Braselton, Georgia, Charles L. Waddell graduated from high school in 1951. He soon found a position as a passenger service officer with American Airlines, moving to the Washington D.C. area and beginning his career at National Airport. In 1962, he transferred to the newly constructed Dulles Airport shortly before its dedication in November of that year. Waddell continued to work for American Airlines at Dulles throughout his career, handing all aspects of the airlines operations. In the early 1960s, he turned his attention to public service. An active Democrat, he was both the Chairman of the Loudoun County Democratic Committee and later the Chairman of the Democratic Committee for the 22nd Senate District before campaigning for and being elected to the Loudoun County Board of Supervisors in 1967, serving the Broad Run District.
In 1971, the 33rd State Senate District was created in Northern Virginia. Waddell ran for the newly elected seat and won, beginning a career as an influential member of the Virginia Senate that would last for 27 years. Waddell served as chairman of the Senate Transportation committee, and transportation served as a key issue in his legislative work. He helped improve roads in Loudoun County, notably shepherding the creation of the Route 28 Transportation Tax District, transforming a two-lane road to a modern highway with multiple interchanges. His legislation also laid groundwork for the Dulles Greenway.
Other issues at the core of Waddell's legislative work included advocating for fair utility charges, environmental issues, and the transportation of nuclear material through Northern Virginia. He also worked to improve education in Virginia, campaigning early in his career for free public text books in schools. Sometimes called the "Singing Senator", Waddell was well known for performing both his at own campaign events and at other public gatherings. In 1998, Waddell stepped down from his Senate seat to take the position of Virginia Secretary of Transportation. Retiring from the office in 2002, he continues to be active in public life, serving three terms on the Herndon Town Council, as the president of the Dumbarton Square Homeowner's Association and as president of the Herndon Historical Society. Waddell received a special recognition certificate at the 2014 Loudoun County History Awards ceremony at the Thomas Balch Library.
Scope and Content
Four scrapbooks document the early decades of Charles Waddell’s political career in Loudoun County. Beginning in the early 1960s when Waddell served as chairman of Loudoun County’s Democratic Committee, continuing through his election to the Loudoun County Board of Supervisors for the Broad Run District in 1967 and his successful campaign in 1971 to become the first State Senator elected in the newly created 33rd State Senate district. Clippings, photographs, and letters in the scrapbooks also record Waddell’s subsequent service as State Senator between 1971 and 1984. The years 1975 and 1979 are particularly well documented.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Senator Charles Waddell Scrapbooks (OM 0022), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Technical Requirements
None
Related Material
Catoctin Dam Project Collection, 1974-1975 (SC 0011), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Contents List
- OM 0022
    - Loose Materials 1982, 1984, 2001
    - Scrapbook, 1976 - 1984, 2001, pages 1-6 1982
    - Scrapbook, 1976 - 1984, 2001, pages 7-12 1981
    - Scrapbook, 1976 - 1984, 2001, pages 13-30 1980
    - Scrapbook, 1976 - 1984, 2001, pages 31-33 1979
    - Scrapbook, 1976 - 1984, 2001, pages 34-48, 1977, Dec.-1978
    - Scrapbook, 1976 - 1984, 2001, pages 49-69 1977, Jan. - Oct.
    - Scrapbook, 1976 - 1984, 2001, pages 70-103 1976
    - Campaign button [boxed] 1975
  - (2)
    - Scrapbook, 1979, pages 1-44
    - Scrapbook, 1979, pages 45-89
    - Scrapbook, 1979, loose bumper sticker
    - Scrapbook, 1975, pages 1-42
    - Scrapbook, 1975, covers with collage, ephemera attached.
  - (3)
    - Scrapbook, 1963 - 1975 loose ephemera
    - Scrapbook, 1963 - 1975, pages 1-18 1975
    - Scrapbook, 1963 - 1975, pages 19-44 1974
    - Scrapbook, 1963 - 1975, pages 45-79 1974
    - Scrapbook, 1963 - 1975, pages 80-112 1972
    - Scrapbook, 1963 - 1975, pages 113-144 1972
    - Scrapbook, 1963 - 1975, pages 145-162 1969, Feb. - 1970
    - Scrapbook, 1963 - 1975, pages 163-184 1969, Jan. - 1963
    - Scrapbook, 1963 - 1975 Cover with bumper stickers